Immigrant Groups in Indiana 1978
Indiana University Digital Library Program
Immigrant Groups in Indiana
1978
Indiana University Center for the Study of History and Memory Indiana University 400 North Sunrise Drive Weatherly Hall North, Room 122 Bloomington, IN 47405 Phone: 812/855-2856 Fax: 812/855-0002 E-mail: ohrc@indiana.edu http://www.indiana.edu/~cshm
Indiana University Center for the Study of History and Memory
ohrc060
15 interviews. Audiotapes, transcripts, and collateral materials.
This collection of interviews deals with different ethnic groups in Indiana between the 1910s and the 1970s. Most of the interviewees are first generation Americans born around the turn of the century. They share their life histories, discussing mainly the World War II era, what they lived through, what brought them to the United States, and how they adjusted to American life. They discuss their native cultures and traditions, as well as their involvement in American life.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains fifteen interviews conducted over the course of one year. The interviews range from fifty minutes to two hours. All interviews consist of audio tapes and most have typed transcripts and collateral materials.
Administrative Information
Acquisition Information
Oral history interviews conducted by the Indiana University Center for the Study of History and Memory from 1968 to the present, with particular focus on the history of twentieth-century America and the Midwest.
Interview List
- Ames, Sylvianne October 17, 1978, 78-041; Not transcribed; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 1 hour 30 minutes; Cooper, Susan
  Access Status
  Open
  Scope and Content Note
  Sylvianne Ames, born in Bordeaux, France in 1941, discusses her early life in France. She also talks about her adjustment to life in the United States.
- Asars, Anna September 21, 1978, 78-027; 49 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 1 hour 30 minutes; no index; Cooper, Susan
  Ana Asars, born in Latvia on June 30, 1898, discusses the obstacles she overcame throughout her life. She talks about both the German and the Russian occupations of her country and the devastation each brought through communist government, deportation and killing. She recalls fleeing Latvia to refugee camps, where she and others were aided by the International Refugee Organization, and describes that life she lived for over three years. Asars speaks of immigrating to America though sponsorship, of her belief that she would soon return home, and of her impressions of the United States, especially her shock at the lack of women's rights. She also talks about her political involvement in the United States.
  Keywords
  Corporation Names
  International Refugee Organization
  Place Names
  Czechoslovakia; Latvia
  Personal Names
  Hefman, Buster
  Subjects
  deportation; German occupation; Immigrant sponsorship; immigration; political involvement; refugee camps; Russian occupation
- Balon, Maria; Balon, Roman October 11, 1978, 78-040; 42 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 1 hour 40 minutes; no index; Cooper, Susan
  Roman and Maria Balon, both born in Poland, share their life stories. They talk about the German occupation in Poland and how it turned their lives upside down even before being deported as teenagers to Germany, where they faced many more hardships. They describe the tragedies that they both witnessed and experienced throughout World War II-- the German occupation, concentration camps, refugee camps, etc.-- as well as the hardships of life during that time. The Balons discuss their original hope of returning home to a free Poland after the war, their realization that Russian control was just as dangerous as that of the Germans, and their consequent decision to immigrate to the United States. They discuss the adjustments they had to make creating a new life in America, especially in learning a new language.
  Germany; Poland; United States
  Americanization; concentration camps; deportation; German occupation; immigration
- Cohen, Habiba; Cohen, William October 7, 1978, 78-036; Not transcribed, 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 1 hour 45 minutes; Cooper, Susan
  Habiba Cohen, born in Iraq in December of 1940, and William Cohen, born in Finland in 1941, discuss their early lives in their respective birthplaces. They share their reasons for immigrating to the United States as well as the problems they faced adjusting. They talk about anti-semitism, especially in academia. The Cohens also speak of cultural traditions and values that they have carried on in the United States.
- Fischel, Henry October 10, 1978, 78-037; Not transcribed; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 1 hour 30 minutes; Cooper, Susan
  Restricted: quotations should not be used out of context
  Henry Fischel, born in Bonn, Germany in 1913, discusses his early life and education in Germany. He discusses the Nazi takeover. Fischel talks about his life as a student at the University of Edinburgh, Scotland as well as in Canada. He speaks of his immigration to the United States and shares information about Jewish studies. He also discusses anti-semitism.
- Goren, Gideon October 5, 1978, 78-034; Not transcribed; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 50 minutes; Cooper, Susan
  Gideon Goren, born in 1933 in Jerusalem, Israel, discusses his early life in Israel. He shares his impressions of America and talks about the Jewish community in Indianapolis, Indiana. Gideon also discusses the function of the Jewish Educational Association (JEA).
- Grunwald, John September 27, 1978, 78-032; 23 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 55 minutes; no index; Cooper, Susan
  John Grunwald, born in 1935 in Budapest, Hungary, discusses his early life in Hungary. He talks about the Nazis and what occurred when they came in 1944. He describes his father's escapes as well as his own, and mentions his mother's inability to get out. Grunwald talks of being smuggled into Austria by a professional smuggler paid by an uncle in the United States, then with the aid of the United States International Refugee Organization, finally making it to the United States. Grunwald recalls his education here and his uncle's desire for him to become Americanized. He gives a brief history of the veneer business of his uncle, where Grunwald has worked. He also talks about Hungarian politics during his lifetime as well as his involvement in American politics.
  Occupation Names
  veneer manufacturer
  Hungary; United States
  Americanization; education; Hungarian politics; immigrant smugglers; political involvement
- Kete, Edwins; Kete, Lydia September, 20, 1978, 78-026; 49 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 1 hour 30 minutes; no index; Cooper, Susan
  Edwins Kete, born on February 8, 1895, and Lydia Kete, born on August 31, 1898, both in Latvia, discuss the hard life and times that they encountered. They describe fleeing to Germany during the Russian occupation in 1944, because there was little other choice. They talk of living in refugee camps and with relatives for five years while Edwins, among other jobs, worked as a translator for the United States Army, before being sponsored to immigrate to the United States. They discuss fleeing to Russia for a time when Germany occupied Latvia, and their hope that after the Russian invasion they would again return to Latvia, which did not come about. They speak of the immigration process, including screening and qualifications. They talk about learning English, and their political involvement in America despite their decision not to become citizens. They also discuss the Latvian immigrant community.
  Latvian Community Center; United States Army
  Germany; Latvia; Russia; United States
  citizenship; German occupation; immigration; learning English; refugee camps; Russian occupation
- Lukins, Marianna September 20, 1978, 78-025; 40 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 1 hour 30 minutes; no index; photograph of interviewee; Cooper, Susan
  Marianna Lukins, born in Latvia on January 1, 1906, discusses the Russian occupation in Latvia and the devastation it caused the country and the people through deportation and seized property. She speaks of the German occupation and why both Germany and Russia would want to overrun Latvia. She recalls the family members she lost to these occupations, including her husband. Lukins fled to Germany with many others in 1944, then to England three years later, where she struggled to make a new life. She explains that she chose to settle in England rather than the United States because she clung to the hope of returning to Latvia and wanted to remain in Europe; this too is why she never sought American citizenship. When her daughters decided to come to America, Marianna came as well to keep the family together. She compares living in the United States with Europe and talks about the Latvian traditions she still practices as well as the now world-wide Latvian community which remains connected.
  Latvian Community Center; United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration
  citizenship; cultural traditions; deportation; German occupation; Latvian community; political involvement; religion; Russian occupation
- Meijers, Ruta J. September 21, 1978, 78-028; 37 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 1 hour 30 minutes; no index; Cooper, Susan
  Ruta J. Meijers, born in Latvia on May 12, 1929, recalls both the Russian and the German occupations, and how they affected her as a child, especially in the area of schooling. She talks about fleeing to Germany and refugee camp life. She discusses the immigration process to the United States, including the screening process and the use of sponsorship. Meijers speaks of Latvian traditions and celebrations, some of which she still upholds, as well as the difficulty she has passing this culture to her children. She discusses her love of Latvia the sadness she feels in being unable to return, and her feeling that although she is an American citizen, she still considers herself Latvian. She talks about her involvement in American politics. She also discusses how she perceives Americans and their treatment of immigrants.
  Germany; Latvia; United States
  citizenship; cultural traditions; German occupation; immigrant screening process; political involvement; refugee camps; Russian occupation
- Ogan, Pekin October 6, 1978, 78-035; Not transcribed; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 1 hour 45 minutes; Cooper, Susan
  Restricted: notification of interviewee prior to publishing a direct quotation
  Pekin Ogan, born in Turkey in April of 1936, discusses his life and education in Turkey. He talks about his impressions of America as well as the problems he faced with his immigration visa. Ogan discusses cultural assimilation along with practice of Turkish traditions. He also talks about the political climate in Turkey.
- Ozolins, Yanis September 29, 1978, 78-033; Not transcribed; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 1 hour 30 minutes; ethnic festival flyer; Cooper, Susan
  Yanis Ozolins, born in Latvia in September of 1939, speaks of his early life in Latvia. He discusses immigrating to the United States, the problems he faced in a new country and the adjustments he had to make. He talks about ethnic identification in Indiana as well as ethnic activities.
- Remak, Henry H. H. October 11, 1978, 78-038; Not transcribed, 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 1 hour 45 minutes; article about interviewee; Cooper, Susan
  Henry H. H. Remak, born in Germany in 1916, discusses his early life and education in both Germany and France. He recalls immigrating to the United States and his impressions of Bloomington, Indiana. Remak discusses anti-semitism. He also speaks of the history of Indiana University.
- Sliwa, Ann; Sliwa, Jozef October 11, 1978, 78-039; Not transcribed; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 2 hours; Cooper, Susan
  Ann and Joseph Sliwa discuss their early lives in Poland. They talk about their deportation to Germany and their experiences during World War II. They also talk about their immigration to the United States.
- Valdmanis, Edgars; Valdmanis, Ivette September 27, 1978, 78-031; 48 pages; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 1 hour 30 minutes; no index; Latvian newspaper; Cooper, Susan
  Edgars Valdmanis, born in 1925 and his wife, Ivette Valmanis, born in 1930, discuss their early lives in Latvia. They talk about both the German and the Russian occupations of their country and the devastation they caused. They also discuss communism, the practice of deportation, and World War II. They speak of their experiences fleeing Latvia in 1944 to refugee camps in various parts of Europe. The Valdmanises discuss beginning again, first in England, then in the United States and the adjustments they had to make to the new culture and the different language. They share their impressions of America prior to arriving as well as after their arrival. They speak in depth about the world-wide Latvian community- especially in England and America- and they express their desire to preserve their culture. They also talk about their political involvement as American citizens, though they remain Latvian at heart.
  England; Latvia; United States
  citizenship; Communism; deportation; German occupation; Latvian community; political involvement; refugee camps; Russian occupation; World War II